Register of the Christopher Temple Emmet Papers 1913-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Christopher Temple Emmet papers,
1913-1974
74105
Emmet, Christopher Temple, 1900-1974
126 manuscript boxes, 5 cubic foot boxes, 9 envelopes, 33 phonorecords (59.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, press releases, writings, recordings of radio broadcasts, and photographs, relating to anti-Nazi and anti-communist movements in the U.S., U.S. foreign policy during the Cold War, and U.S.-German relations.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
American Council on Germany.; American Friends of the Captive Nations.; Anti-Nazi movement.; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Germany.; Germany--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Politics and government.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Foreign relations--Germany.; Phonorecords.; Phonotapes.
Biographical Note
1900, March 18 Born, New York City
1919-1920 Attended Harvard University
1920's Attended University of Freiburg
1938 Secretary, Volunteer Christian Committee to Boycott Nazi Germany
1940 Chairman, Committee to Aid Britain by Reciprocal Trade
Vice president, France Forever
Member, executive committee, Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies
1942 Moderator, Foreign Affairs Round Table, Station WEVD, New York
1945 Chairman, Committee Against Mass Expulsions
1946 Treasurer, Committee for a Fair Trial for Draja Mihailovich
Member, board of trustees, Freedom House
1947 Organizer, Committee for a Just Peace with Italy
Member, board of directors, Common Cause
1951 Executive vice president, American Council on Germany
Member, board of directors, International Rescue Committee
1955 Member, executive committee, American Friends of Vietnam
1956 Chairman, American Friends of the Captive Nations
1958 Vice chairman, Emergency Committee for U.N. Action on Hungary
1959 Delegate, Atlantic Congress, London
1974 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Christopher Temple Emmet was also known as Christopher Temple Emmet, Jr.
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1940-1972
  Biographical notes, correspondence, memoranda and miscellanea, arranged by subject.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Biographical notes
  - Family correspondence
  - Testimonial dinner, New York, November 9, 1961
    - General
    - Correspondence
- SUBJECT FILE, 1938-1974
  Correspondence, memoranda, clippings, press releases, printed matter, and financial records, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Acheson, Dean - Controversy with George F. Kennan, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Clippings
      - Foreign
      - U.S. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
  - Adenauer, Chancellor Konrad
  - Agriculture - Russia
  - Aid Refugee Chinese Intellectuals
    - Correspondence
    - Financial records
    - Memoranda
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Printed matter
  - Akers, Anthony B. (Box 3)
  - Alaska - Defenses
  - Algeria
  - Allen-Bradley Company
  - Alliance, Inc.
  - American Afro-Asian Educational Exchange
  - American-Asian Educational Exchange
  - American Association for a Democratic Germany
  - American Baltic Commemorative Committee
  - American Boycott Against Aggressor Nations
  - American China Policy Association
  - American Christian Alliance
  - American Citizens' Committee to Commemorate the Tenth Anniversary of the Hungarian Revolution
  - American Civil Liberties Union
  - American Committee for Aid to Katanga Freedom Fighters
  - American Committee for Cultural Freedom
  - American Committee for International Information (Box 4)
  - American Committee on Africa
  - American Committee on Liberation
  - American Committee on United Europe
  - American Council Against Nazi Propaganda
  - American Council on Germany
    - Correspondence
    - Financial records
    - Fundraising campaign material
    - Memoranda
      - General
      - Planning Committee
    - Press releases and clippings
    - Reports of activities
  - American Council on NATO
    - Memoranda
      - General
      - Proposed merger with Atlantic Citizens' Congress
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Miscellaneous
    - Printed matter
  - American Emergency Committee for Tibetan Refugees (Box 5)
  - American Federation of Labor
  - American Friends of the Captive Nations
    - Aims
    - Appeal for amnesty in Hungary
    - Bank statements
      - 1962
      - 1963
      - 1964
      - 1965-1966
      - 1967-1968
      - 1969-1973
    - Bills (Box 6)
      - 1961
      - 1962
      - 1963
      - 1964
      - 1965-1967
      - 1968-1973
    - Certificate of incorporation
    - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - Financial statements
      - 1959-1970
      - 1960-1970
    - Fundraising campaign material
      - 1957-1960
      - 1958
      - 1959
      - 1960
      - 1963
      - 1964
    - Hungary boycott pledge
    - Hungary under Soviet Rule project
      - Volume I, 1957
        - Correspondence
        - Financial records
        - Memoranda
        - Minutes of meetings (Box 8)
        - Printed copy
        - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Volume II, 1958
        - Correspondence
        - Financial records
        - Memoranda
        - Printed copy
        - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Volume III, 1959
        - Correspondence
        - Memoranda
        - Printed matter
      - Volume IV, 1960
        - Correspondence
        - Memoranda
        - Printed copy
        - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Volume V, 1961
        - Correspondence
        - Memoranda
        - Printed copy
        - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Volume VI, 1962
        - Correspondence
        - Memoranda
        - Printed copy (Box 9)
        - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Volume VII, 1963
    - Liberation Rally, New York, May 25, 1956
    - Membership lists and correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Minutes of meetings
      - 1957
      - 1958
      - 1959
      - 1960
      - 1961
    - Miscellany (Box 10)
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter
    - Proposed conference, 1957
    - Proposed Germany-East Europe conference, May 1959
    - Public relations material
    - Questionnaire for Congressmen
      - 1960
        - Questionnaire
        - Replies
      - 1962
      - 1964
        - Questionnaire
        - Replies
    - Registration as charity (Box 11)
    - Reports of activities
    - Resolution on Hungary and the Middle East
    - Response to Better Business Bureau questionnaire
    - Revolt in Hungary film project
    - Tax records
      - Federal
      - State
  - American Friends of Vietnam
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Drafts of writings (Box 12)
    - Financial records
    - Memoranda
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Notes
    - Printed matter, miscellaeous
  - American-German Conferences (Box 13)
    - 1st, Bad Godesberg, October 1-4, 1959
    - 2d, Washington, February 16-19, 1961
    - 4th, Berlin, November 12-15, 1964
    - 7th, November 15, 1971
  - American-German Youth Conference, 1st, Hamburg, June 27-30, 1973
  - American Humanist Association
  - American Hungarian Federation
  - American Institute on Germany Today
  - American Irish Defense Association
  - American Legion
  - American Veterans of World War II
  - American Zionist Council
  - Americans for Democratic Action
  - Americans for Intellectual Freedom - Freedom House Rally in opposition to Cultural and Scientific Conference for World Peace, New York, March 1949
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Speeches
  - Americans for Winning the Peace
  - Americans United for World Government
  - Amnesty for Political Prisoners in Hungary
  - Anticommunist movements - U.S.
    - General
    - Proposed united front, 1946
  - Antisemitism (Box 14)
    - Europe, Eastern
    - Germany
    - Russia
  - Argentine Republic - Politics and government-1943-1955
  - Armstrong, Representative O. K. - Proposal for anticommunist conference, July 1956
  - Asian Peoples' Anti-Communist League
  - Assassination - U.S.
  - Assembly of Captive European Nations
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter
  - Atlantic Council of the United States
  - Atlantic Union Committee
  - Atlantik-Bruecke (Atlantic Bridge)
  - Atomic power - International control (Box 15)
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter
  - Atomic weapons - Testing
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter, miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Atomic weapons and disarmament
  - Australia - Foreign relations
  - Austria - History - Allied occupation, 1945-1955
  - Bandera, Stepan
  - Bang-Jensen, Povl
  - Berger, Liselotte
  - Berlin. Conference, 1945
  - Berlin question (1945- )
  - Berlin Wall (1961- )
  - Bevan, Aneurin
  - Blumenfeld, Erik
  - Boeker, Alexander
  - Bormann, Martin
  - Bowles, Chester
  - Brandt, Karl
  - British War Relief Society
  - Brzezinski, Zbigniew
  - Bundy, William P.
  - CARE
  - "Captive nations" - Definition of term
  - Captive Nations Week
    - 1959
    - 1960 (Box 17)
    - 1961
    - 1962
    - 1963
    - 1964
    - 1965
    - 1966 (Box 18)
    - 1967
    - 1968
    - 1969
    - 1970
    - 1971
    - 1973
  - Carl Schurz Memorial Foundation
  - Catholic Church and communism
  - Catholics in the U.S.
  - Chennault, General Claire
  - Cherne, Leo
  - Chiang, Kai-shek, President
  - Chile - Politics and government
  - China - United Nations membership
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter
  - "China Lobby" (Box 19)
  - Chinese News Service
  - Churchill, Prime Minister Winston
  - Citizens' Boycott Rally Against Nazi Aggression, New York, March 27, 1939
  - Citizens Committee for a Free Cuba
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter
  - Citizens Committee for Peace with Freedom in Vietnam
  - Citizens Committee for Peace with Security
  - City College of New York Invitational Debate Tournament, 4th New York, April 4, 1959
  - Civil rights
    - Russia
    - Ukraine
  - Cohn, August
  - Cold War Council
  - Colgate Foreign Policy Conference, 1958
  - Committee Against Mass Expulsions
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Drafts of writings
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter, miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Reports
  - Committee Against the Recognition of Red Hungary
  - Committee for a Democratic Policy Toward China
  - Committee for a Fair Trial for Draja Mihailovich
    - Clippings
    - Commission of Inquiry material
    - Contributions
    - Correspondence (Box 21)
    - Financial records
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter, miscellaneous
  - Committee for a Free China (Box 22)
  - Committee for a Free Europe
  - Committee for a Just Peace with Italy
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter, miscellaneous
  - Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy
  - Committee for Return of Confiscated German and Japanese Property
  - Committee of Czechoslovak Ambulance in France
  - Committee of One Million
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Drafts and notes (Box 23)
    - Financial records
    - Information kit
    - Memoranda
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Pamphlets
    - Press releases
    - Publicity and fundraising material
  - Committee on National Affairs
  - Committee to Aid Britain by Reciprocal Trade
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Speeches
  - Committee to Defend America by Aiding the Allies (Box 24)
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter
    - Speeches
  - Committee to Restore Lithuania's Independence
  - Common Cause
    - Clippings
    - Correspondence
    - Freedom Rally, New York, May 5, 1949
    - Hold Berlin Rally, New York, May 24, 1950
    - Memoranda
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter, miscellaneous
  - Communication - U.S.
  - Communism
    - General
      - Drafts of writings
      - Printed matter
    - Canada (Box 25)
    - China
      - Clippings
      - Correspondence
      - Memoranda
      - Notes
      - Pamphlets
      - Printed matter, miscellaneous
      - Speeches
    - Cuba
    - Czechoslovak Republic
    - Europe, Eastern
    - Germany, West
    - Hungary
    - Poland
    - Rumania (Box 26)
    - Russia
    - Ukraine
    - U.S.
    - Yugoslavia
  - Conant, James Bryant
  - Conference Group on German Politics
  - Conference of Americans of Central-East European Descent
  - Conference of Foreign Ministers, Geneva, 1959
  - Conference on European Problems, 7th, Rockville, Maryland, October 7-10, 1971
  - Conference on Psychological Strategy in the Cold War, Washington, February 22-23, 1952
  - Conference on the Berlin Problem and the Future of Eastern Europe, Chicago, March 22-25, 1962
    - Miscellaneous
    - Papers presented
  - Congress for Cultural Freedom
  - Conservative Rally for World Liberation from Communism, New York, March 7, 1962
  - Constitutions
  - Coordinating Center for Democratic Opinion
  - Coordinating Council for Democracy
  - Coste, Brutus
  - Council Against Communist Aggression
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda (Box 27)
  - Council Against Intolerance in America
  - Council for Democracy
  - Council of All-Russian Nationalists
  - Council of Europe
  - Council on Foreign Relations
    - General
    - Discussion Group on U.S. Policy Toward the Soviet Satellites in Eastern Europe
    - Study Group on Communist China and U.S. Policy in Asia
    - Study Group on Indo-China
    - Study Group on the German Democratic Republic and Germany's Future
    - Study Group on Yugoslavia and Eastern Europe (Box 28)
  - Counterattack
  - Crimea Conference, Yalta, Russia, 1945
  - Crown of St. Stephen
  - Cuba - History - Invasion, 1961
    - General
    - Prisoners
  - Cuban Missile Crisis, October 1962
  - Cultural and Scientific Conference for World Peace, New York, March 25-27, 1949
    - Clippings
    - Press releases
  - Curtis, Senator Carl T. (Box 29)
  - Cyprus
  - Czechoslovak Republic - History - Intervention, 1968
  - Dardanelles
  - Declaration of Atlantic Unity
  - Decter, Moshe
  - Democratic Party (U.S.) - Platform
    - 1956 - "Captive nations" plank
    - 1960 - "Captive nations" plank
    - 1964 - "Captive nations" plank
  - Democratic Party of Vietnam
  - Deportation
    - Czechoslovak Republic
    - Poland
    - Sudetenland
    - Ukraine
  - De Rochefort, Nicholas
  - Diem, President Ngo Dinh
  - Disarmament
    - Clippings
    - Memoranda
    - Proposed Committee for Safe Disarmament
  - Dobriansky, Lev E.
  - Dodd, Senator Thomas J. (Box 30)
    - General
    - Censure by Senate
      - Clippings
      - Memoranda
    - Freedom and Foreign Policy
  - Dominican Republic - History - Invasion, 1965
  - Douglas, Senator Paul H.
  - Dulles, John Foster
  - Dumbarton Oaks Conference, 1944
  - Durholz, Otto
  - Dushnyck, Walter
  - Eibel, Ryszard
  - Elections (Box 31)
    - Germany, West
      - 1957
      - 1966
      - 1972
    - Hungary - 1958
    - U.S.
      - 1960
      - 1962
      - 1964
  - Emergency Civil Liberties Committee
  - Emergency Committee for U.N. Action on Hungary
    - Correspondence
    - Endorsements
    - Financial records
    - Membership lists and correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Memoranda (Box 32)
    - Poll of Congressmen on Hungarian membership in U.N.
      - Letters to Congressmen
      - Responses
    - Poll of editors and publishers
    - Press releases
    - Printed matter
  - Epstein, Julius
  - Espionage, Russian
  - Europe - Defenses
  - Europe, Eastern - Economic conditions
  - European Economic Community
  - European federation (Box 33)
  - European Security Conference, proposed
  - Export controls
  - Far Eastern Information Service
  - Fascism - Germany
  - Federal Union, Inc.
  - Fight for Freedom Committee to Defend America
  - Finland - Foreign relations
  - Fischer, Ruth
  - Fitch, Geraldine T.
  - Fontaine, Andre
  - Forced labor - Russia
  - Foreign Policy Association
  - Foreign propagandists in the U.S.
  - Forensic Foundation
  - Foundation for Religious Action in the Social and Civil Order
  - Foundation to Defeat Communism
  - France
    - Colonies
    - Foreign relations
    - History - German occupation, 1940-1944
      - Memoranda and notes
      - Printed matter
  - France Forever
    - Correspondence
    - Drafts of writings
    - Memoranda
  - Fraternal Order of Eagles (Box 34)
  - Free China Fund
  - Free Europe Committee
    - Correspondence
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter
  - Freedom House
    - General
    - 1942-1945
    - 1946-1959
    - 1961-1962
    - 1963-1964
    - 1965-1966
    - 1967-1968
    - 1969-1970
    - 1971-1972 (Box 35)
    - 1973
    - Post-Election Conference on City Affairs, New York, November 30-December 1, 1945
  - Freedom Studies Center
  - Friedrich Ebert Stiftung (Friedrich Ebert Foundation)
  - Friends of Democracy
  - Friends of Russian Freedom
  - Fund for the Republic
  - Gaulle, President Charles de
  - General Federation of Women's Clubs
  - German-American Conference, 2d, Wiesbaden, September 8-12, 1963
  - German reunification question (1949- ) (Box 36)
  - Germans in the Czechoslovak Republic
  - Germany
    - Boundaries - Poland
    - Defenses
    - History
      - 1918-1933
      - Allied occupation, 1945-1955
  - Germany, West
    - Foreign relations
      - General
      - France
      - "Ostpolitik" (Eastern policy)
      - Russia
    - Foreign economic relations - China
    - Military policy
    - Politics and government (Box 37)
    - Treaties, etc. Russia, 1970
  - Globke, Hans
  - Gray, Adeline
  - Great Britain
    - British Information Service
    - Foreign relations
      - General
      - China
  - Greek War Relief Association
  - Grewe, Ambassador Wilhelm
  - Group Research, Inc.
  - Guttenberg, Karl Theodor Freiherr von und zu
  - Guyana - Politics and government
  - Hahn, Emily
  - Harriman, Ambassador W. Averell
  - Help Free Hungary Rally, New York, November 8, 1956
  - Herter, Christian A.
  - Hess, Rudolf
  - Hirsch, Felix E.
  - Hiss, Alger
  - Hlasko, Marek
  - Hoover, President Herbert
  - Hoover, J. Edgar, Masters of Deceit
  - Hull, Cordell
  - Human Events
  - Hungarian National Council
  - Hungary
    - History
      - General
      - Revolution, 1956
        - General
        - General (Box 38)
        - Civilian relief
        - 1st anniversary
        - 2d anniversary
        - 5th anniversary
        - 10th anniversary
    - United Nations membership
      - Correspondence
      - Memoranda (Box 39)
      - Press releases
      - Printed matter
      - Proposed resolutions for expulsion (Box 40)
  - India
    - Foreign relations
    - Independence
  - Indonesia - History - Revolution, 1945-1949
  - Institute of International Education
  - Institute of Pacific Relations
  - Intellectuals - Germany
  - Interim Commission on Food and Agriculture
  - Interim Committee on U.S. Support of NATO
  - International Anti-Communist Entente
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom
  - International Conference on the Political Warfare of the Soviets, Paris, December 1-3, 1960
  - International Council of Women
  - International Labour Conference
  - International Peasant Union
  - International Refugee Organization
  - International Rescue Committee
    - Correspondence
    - Financial records
    - Memoranda (Box 41)
    - Minutes of meetings
    - Printed matter
  - International Research in Communist Techniques, Inc.
  - International Study Conference on the Atlantic Community, 2d, Copenhagen, August 30-September 5, 1953
  - Iraq - History - Revolution, 1958
  - Isolationism - U.S.
  - Israel - Foreign relations
  - Israel-Arab War, 1967
  - Jaksch, Wenzel
  - Japanese-Americans
  - Javits, Senator Jacob K.
  - Jewish War Veterans of the U.S.A.
  - John LaFarge Institute
  - Joint Boycott Council of the American Jewish Congress and the Jewish Labor Committee
  - Jonas, Pal (Box 42)
  - Josten, Josef
  - Judd, Representative Walter H.
  - Justice for Poland Rally, New York, September 23, 1945
  - Kalmuk Committee to Combat Bolshevism
  - Kaskell, Joseph
  - Katz, Stephen
  - Kennedy, President John F.
  - Kesler, Bruce
  - Khrushchev, Nikita
    - General
    - Visit to the United Nations, 1960
    - Visit to the U.S., 1959
      - Correspondence
      - Memoranda
      - Printed matter
  - King-Hall, Stephen
  - Kiss, Sandor
  - Knauth, Theodore W. (Box 43)
  - Koevago, Mayor Joseph
  - Kohlberg, Alfred
  - Korean-American Council
  - Korean reunification question (1945- )
  - Korean War, 1950-1953
    - General
    - China
    - Peace
    - Prisoners and prisons
  - Kosenkina, Oksana
  - Kraft, Ole Bjorn
  - Kravchenko, Viktor A.
  - Labor-Management Relations Act, 1947
  - Langerhans, Heinz
  - Latin America - Politics
  - Lattimore, Owen
  - League for Freedom
  - League for Industrial Democracy
  - Lebanon - History - Intervention, 1958
  - Lewis, Daniel H.
  - Lewis, Fulton, Jr.
  - Liberal Party Dinner Forum, New York, August 2, 1944 (Box 44)
  - Liberty of speech
  - Lighthouse Committees
  - Lindsay, Mayor John V.
  - Lithuanian American Council
  - Lodge, Ambassador Henry Cabot
  - Luce, Clare Boothe
  - Lynching - U.S.
  - MacArthur, General Douglas - Dismissal, 1951
  - McCarthy, Senator Joseph R.
  - McDowell, Arthur G.
  - McLain, Charles Albert
  - Maleter, General Pal
  - Manchuria
  - Marcuse, Herbert
  - Marshall Plan
  - Martin, David
    - General
    - Ally Betrayed
    - "How to Falsify Military Intelligence"
    - Testimonial dinner, Washington, February 6, 1974
  - Meany, George
  - Meeting of Heads of Government and Chiefs of State, Paris, 1960
  - Meeting of Heads of Government of France, United Kingdom, Soviet Union, and United States, Geneva, 1955
    - Memoranda
    - Printed matter (Box 45)
  - Mikoyan, Anastas I. - Visit to the U.S., 1959
  - Military assistance, American - Pakistan
  - Mindszenty, Joseph Cardinal
  - Miscellany
  - Moral Re-Armament (organization)
  - Morocco
  - Moscow trial, 1945
  - Mosley, Sir Oswald
  - Movement for the Defense of the Hungarian Nation in the United Nations
  - Muhlen, Norbert
  - Multilateral Nuclear Force
  - Nagy, Imre
  - Nansen, Odd
  - National Association of Manufacturers
  - National Committee for Justice for Dodd
  - National Committee for the Defense of South Vietnam Against Communist Aggression
  - National Community Relations Advisory Council
  - National Conference on Freedom and Peace through Liberation
  - National Conference on Spiritual Foundations, 3d, Washington, March 18-20, 1957
  - National Council of American-Soviet Friendship (Box 46)
  - National Economic Council
  - National Humane Society
  - National Non-Partisan Committee for the Re-Election of Senator Dodd
  - National Review
  - National socialism
  - National Student Coordinating Committee for Freedom in Vietnam and Southeast Asia
  - Nationaldemokratische Partei Deutschlands (National Democratic Party of Germany)
  - Nationalism - Germany
  - New School for Social Research
  - Nixon, President Richard M.